上一节，我们讨论了如何解模线性方程
In the previous segment, we talked about
how to solve modular linear equations.
本节我们将讨论如何解模二次方程
In this segment, we're gonna talk about how
to solve modular quadratic equations.
更一般地，我们要看如何计算模e次方根。如我所说
And more generally, we're gonna talk about how
to compute modular e'th roots. As I said,
我们现在知道如何去解线性方程了，通过使用求逆的算法
now we know how to solve linear equations
simply by using an inversion algorithm to
来计算一个数的逆，然后乘以-B。问题是
compute a inverse and then multiplying
the result by minus B. So the question is
怎么解高次多项式方程呢？我们特别感兴趣的是
what about higher degree polynomials and
in particular we are interested in
解质数模多项式方程，解Z_p中的多项式方程
solving, polynomials modulo primes. So
solving polynomials in ZP, but polynomials
特别是形如x^2-c或y^3-c或z^37-c，全部在Z_p中
particularly of the form x squared - c
or y cubed - c or z to the 37 - c, all in ZP.
解这个多项式方程，例如，计算C的平方根
So solving this polynomial, for
example, involved computing the square root of C.
解这个多项式方程，计算C的立方根
Solving this polynomial
involves computing the cube root of C.
解这个多项式方程，计算C的37次方根。等等。。
Solving this polynomial involves computing
the thirty-seventh root of C. And so on.
那么我们固定质数p，我们说C是Z_p中的某元素
So, again, let's fix the primes P, and
let's say that C is some element in ZP.
我们说在Z_p中，X满足X的e次方等于C
We'll say that X in ZP that satisfies X to
the E is equal to C. We'll call such an X
我们就说X是C的e次方根。那么我们来看一个例子
the modular E-th root of C. So let's look
at an example. We say that the cube root
我们说在Z_11中，7的立方根等于6，
因为6的立方等于216
of 7 in Z11 is equal to 6,
because 6 cubed is equal to 216, which
216 = 7 mod 11。因此，7模11的立方根
happens to be 7 modulo 11. And
therefore, the cube root of 7 modulo 11
等于6。我问大家，在Z_11中，3的平方根是多少？
is equal to 6. So let me ask you,
what is the square root of 3 in Z11?
答案是5，因为5的平方是25，也就是3模11
So the answer is 5 because 5
squared is equal to 25, which is 3 modulo 11.
类似地，我问大家，1的模11立方根是什么？
And similarly, let me ask
you, what is the cubed root of 1, modulo 11.
1的立方根就是1，因为1的立方等于1，在Z_11中
Well the cube root of 1
is simply 1, because one cubed is equal to 1, in Z11.
事实上这点对所有质数模都成立
In fact that's true
in modulo any prime. One thing I'd like to
我想指出一点，这些e次方根不一定总是存在的。例如
point out is that these e'th roots
don't always exist. For example, if I
如果我让大家去计算2模11的平方根，就会有问题
asked you to compute the square root of
2 modulo 11, you'd have a problem,
因为2模11的平方根是不存在的
because the square root of two simply
doesn't exist modulo 11. So now that
现在我们理解了e次方根的意义。下一问题是
we understand what an e'th root is, the next
question is, when do these e'th roots
什么时候这些e次方根存在？当我们知道它们存在时
我们能否有效地计算它们？
exist, and when we know that they do
exist, can we actually compute them efficiently?
那么我们看一个简单例子。这个简单例子是
So, let's start with the easy
case. The easy case is, when we want to
当我们想计算某个数的e次方根时，
正好有e与p-1互质
compute an e'th root of something, and it
so happens that e is relatively prime to p-1.
这时c^(1/e)始终存在，且有一非常容易的算法
In this case, c to the one over
e always exists, and there's a very easy
可以计算出c在Z_p中的e次方根。我们来看怎么办
algorithm to actually compute the e'th root
of c in ZP. So let's see how this works.
首先，因为e与p-1互质，我们知道e模p-1有逆
So first, since e is relatively prime to
p-1, we know that e has an inverse
我们计算这个逆，并记之为d
modulo of p-1. So let's compute
this inverse, and let's call it d.
那么我们让d表示e模p-1的逆。然后我宣称，事实上c^(1/e)
So let's let d be the inverse of e modulo p-1. Then I claim that in fact c to the 1/e
就是c^d mod p。如果这个等式成立
is simply c to the d,
modulo p. So if this equation holds then
那么首先它证明了对Z_p中的所有c，c的e次方根
first of all it proves that for all
с in ZP the e'th root to c actually
总是存在。进一步地，它给出了一个非常有效的算法
来计算c的e次方根
exists. And moreover, it gives a very
efficient algorithm to compute this e'th root to c,
通过简单计算e模p-1的逆
simply by computing the inverse
of e modulo p-1, and then raising
然后计算c的逆次方。一举两得
c to the power of that inverse. Okay? So
we kill two birds in one stone. So let's
我们看这个方程为何成立。首先，一个事实是
see why this equation holds. So first of
all the fact that d times e is equal to
d*e =1 mod p-1，这意味着存在某个整数k，使得
one mod p-1, what that means is there
exists some integer k. Such that if I look
如果我看d*e，它将等于k(p-1)+1
at d times e for that's basically gonna be
k times p-1 plus 1. That's basically
(这里是看普通整数乘法。总是存在k这样的整数)
这个的意思就是d*e = 1 mod p-1
what it means that d times e is equal to
one modulo p-1. Well, so now we can
现在我们可以确认c^d是c的一个e次方根了
actually confirm that c to the d is a
e'th root of C. Well, how do we
我们如何确定？取c^d，计算它的e次方
confirm that? Well, let's take C to the D,
and raise it to the power of E. If in
如果c^d真是c的一个e次方根，那么当我们计算它的e次方
fact, c to the d is an e'th root of
c, when we raise it to the power of e;
我们应该会得到c。那么我们看为什么是这样
we're supposed to get c back. So let's see
why that's true. Well, that's simply equal
这等于c^(d*e)
to c times d to the e, and c times d to
the e, well, by definition, is equal to c
(口误，应为c to d times e)
等于c^(k(p-1)+1)，使用指数法则
to the power of k times p-1 plus 1
Well, using the laws of
我们可以把这个写成c^(k(p-1))*c
exponentiation, we can write this as c to
the power of p-1 to the power of k times c.
我这里使用了标准的指数法则，分配幂
All I did is I distributed the
exponentiation using the standard laws of exponentiation.
现在关于c^(p-1)我们知道什么？因为c在Z_p中
Now what do we know about
c to the p-1? Since c lives in ZP
根据费马定理，我们知道在Z_p中，c^(p-1)=1
by Fermat's theorem we know that c
to the p-1 is equal to 1, in ZP.
1的k次方依然是1，因此这个在Z_p中等于c
1 to the k is also equal to 1 and as a
result, this is simply equal to c in ZP,
这正是我们需要证明的，c^d是c的e次方根
which is exactly what we needed to prove
that c to the d is an e'th root of c.
好，那么这就是我说的简单情况。
事实上当e与p-1互质时
Okay. So this is what I call the easy
case. In fact, the e'th root always exists
e次方根总是存在。根是容易计算的
when e is relatively prime to p-1. And it's very easy to compute it
只要使用这里的公式即可。现在我们看一个难一些的情况
simply by using this formula here. Now
let's turn to the less easy case. So the
当e与p-1不互质时。一个经典的例子是
less easy case is when e is not relatively
prime to p-1. And the canonical example
当e=2的情况。现在假设我们想计算在Z_p中
here is when e is equal to 2. So now
suppose we want to compute square roots of
c的平方根。那么如果p是一个奇质数，事实上
从今往后我们一直都关心奇质数
c in ZP. So if p is an odd prime, and in
fact we are going to focus on odd primes
事实上p-1是欧氏，意味着2整除p-1
from now on, then in fact p-1 is going to
be even. Which means that two are divided
gcd(2,p-1)确实不等于1，所以这不是容易的情况
p-1, and indeed the gcd(2,p-1) is
not equal to 1, So this is not the easy case.
所以我们上一张幻灯片里看到的算法，在这里不适用
So the algorithm that we just saw on
the previous slide is not gonna work when
我们想计算奇质数模的平方根
we want to compute square roots modulo
an odd prime.
那么当我们工作在奇质数模下，平方函数实际上是2到1函数
So when we work modulo odd prime, the squaring function is actually a
2-to-1 function. Namely, it maps X and
(本质上，这个平方函数也是一个群同态)
它把X和-X映射到了同一个值。它把它们都映射到了X^2。因此
minus X to the same value. It matched both
of them to X squared. And as a result, we
我们说这个函数是2到1函数。这是一个简单的例子
say that this function is a 2-to-1
function. So here's a simple example.
我们看当我们计算模11的平方，会发生什么
Let's look at what happens when we compute
squares modulo eleven. So you can see that
那么大家可以看到，1和-1模11都被映射到了1。
2和-2模11都被映射到了4
1 and -1 modulo 11 both map
to 1. 2 and -2 both map to 4.
3和-3都被映射到了9，等等。。
3 and -3  both map to
9, and so on and so forth, So you can
所以大家可以看到这是一个2到1映射。那么
事实上这些元素：1, 4
see that it's a 2-to-1 map. So, in
fact, these elements here, 1, 4,
9, 5, 3, 都是有平方根的。例如
9, 5, 3, all are gonna have square roots. For example, the square root
4的平方根是2和9。我宣称，事实上
of 4 is simply gonna be 2 and 9.
And I claim that, in fact, none of the
Z_11里的其他元素都没有平方根
other elements of Z11 are gonna have
a square root. And that motivates this
这就引出了这个定义，说一个Z_p中的元素x，
我们称之为一个二次剩余
definition to say that an element x in ZP,
we're gonna say, is called a quadratic
如果事实上它在Z_p中有一个平方根。如果它没有
residue. If in fact, it has a square root
in ZP. Okay, and if it doesn't have a
平方根，我们就称之为二次非剩余
square root, we'll say that it's a non
quadratic residue. For example modulo 11
例如4模11是一个二次剩余，9也是二次剩余
4 is going to be a quadratic
residue, 9 is a quadratic residue, 5
5是二次剩余，3是二次剩余，当然
is a quadratic residue, 3 is a
quadratic residue, and, of course, 1 is
1也是二次剩余。那么我问大家，如果p是一个奇质数
a quadratic residue. So let me ask you, if
p is an odd prime, what do you think is
你觉得Z_p中的二次剩余一共有多少个？
我给大家一个提示
the number of quadratic residues in ZP?
And I'll give you a hint; the squaring
这个平方函数是2到1的映射，意味着Z_p中
有一半的元素在这个映射中没有原像
function is a 2-to-1 map, which means
that half the elements in ZP can't have a
所以二次剩余的总数是(p-1)/2 + 1
pre-image under this map. So the number of
quadratic residues is simply (p-1)/2 + 1
原因是因为我们知道Z_p中的一半元素
And the reason that's
true is because we know that exactly half
是二次剩余的
the elements in ZP are gonna be
quadratic residues, Because of the fact
因为平方函数是2到1映射。所以映射的像
that the squaring function is a 2-to-1
map. So there can be, at most (p-1)/2
最多有(p-1)/2个元素。那么Z_p中的一半的元素
elements in the image of that
map. So half the elements in ZP are
是二次剩余的。那么在Z_p中还有0也是二次剩余的
quadratic residues, And then, in ZP,
there's also zero. We also have to account
我们也必须包括0，0总是二次剩余的，因为0的平方是0
for zero. Zero is always a quadratic
residue, 'cause zero squared is equal to
所以我们在Z_p^*里有(p-1)/2个二次剩余
zero. So overall, we get (p-1)/2
quadratic residues in ZP*, plus 1,
再加上Z_p里的0也是二次剩余。那么Z_p中一共
the zero element, which is a quadratic
residue in ZP. So overall, in ZP, there
有(p-1)/2 + 1个二次剩余。好，要记住的要点是
are (p-1)/2 + 1 quadratic
residues. Okay, so the main points to
约有一半的元素有平方根，另一半则没有
remember is that roughly half the elements
have a square root and the other half does
我想强调，这和容易的情况很不同
not have a square root. I wanna emphasize
that this is very different from the easy
容易的情况下，e与p-1互质。如果大家记得
case, where e was relatively prime to p-1. If you remember in the easy
在容易的情况里，Z_p的每一个元素都有一个e次方根，
当e与p-1不互质的时候
case, every element in ZP had an e'th
root. When e is not relatively prime to p-1,
不再是这种情况了，特别地，当e=2
that's no longer the case, and
in particular in the case of e equals 2,
Z_p中只有一半的元素有平方根
only half of the elements in ZP have
a square root. Well, so the natural
那么自然就有问题，我们能否对Z_p^*里的一个元素X
question then is, can we given an element x
that's in ZP*, can we tell whether it has
判断出X是否有平方根呢？那么欧拉对此做了重要工作
a square root or not? So Euler did some
important work on that too and in fact, he
他提出了一个非常清楚的测试这些元素
came up with a very clean criteria to test
exactly which elements are quadratic
是否是二次剩余的标准。特别地，他说
residues and which are not. And in
particular he said that x in ZP is a
在Z_p中，x是二次剩余，当且仅当x的(p-1)/2次方等于1模p
quadratic residue if and only if x to the
power of (p-1)/2 is equal to 1 modulo p.
非常优雅简洁的条件。我们来看一个Z_11的简单例子
Okay, very, very elegant and very simple condition. Let's see a simple
当我们工作在模11下时，这里我为大家计算了
example in Z11, so when we work mod 11. So here I compute it at the 5th
所有Z_11里的元素的5次幂，那么大家可以看到这个符号
power of all the elements in Z11 for
you, and you can see that this symbol,
X^((p-1)/2)始终是1或-1
this X to the (p-1)/2, is
always either one or minus one, and it's
在二次剩余1,3,4,5,9上，它一定是1
one precisely at the quadratic
residues--so 1, 3, 4, 5, and 9.
好，那些就是二次剩余，而其他元素不是二次剩余
Okay, those are the quadratic
residues, and the other elements are not
这里，我用绿色圈出，这些元素
quadratic residues. Here, I'll circle them
in green. These are the elements that do
没有平方根，当我们工作在模11下。我想指出一点
not have a square root when we work modulo
11. One thing I'd like to point out
事实上，如果我们取一个非0的数x，我们看x的(p-1)/2次方
is, in fact, if we take an x that's not
equal to 0, and we look at x to the (p-1)/2
我们可以把它写成x^(p-1)的平方根
Well, we can write that as the square root of x to the p-1
把二分之一提取出来了，然后这就是
The kind of, the half bubbles out, and this is simply the square
x^(p-1)的平方根。根据费马小定理，x^(p-1)=1
root of x to the p-1. Well, x to
the p-1 by Fermat's theorem, is 1.
所以x^((p-1)/2)就是1的平方根，也就一定是1或-1
So, x to the (p-1)/2 is
simply a square root of 1, which must be 1 or -1.
这就证明了这个幂
So what this proves is that really this exponentiation here must
一定输出1或-1，我们实际上看到过了
output 1 or -1, and we actually
saw that happening here. It outputs 1
当x是二次剩余时，它输出1；当x不是二次剩余时，它输出-1
when x is a quadratic residue, and it
outputs -1 when x is not a
这个证明不难
quadratic residue. This is not a
particularly difficult proof, but I'm not
(提示：依然是拉格朗日定理的直接推论)
但我这里不给出，本章末我会给大家指出一份参考
going to show it to you here. It's in the
reference that I point to you at the end
为求完整，我说一下，这个值：x^((p-1)/2)
of the module. And just for completeness,
I'll mention that this value, x to the (p-1)/2
有个名字叫勒让德符号(x/p)
has a name, it's called the Legendre's symbol of x over p.
如我们所说，Z_p中所有元素的勒让德符号不是1就是-1
And as we said, this for elements in ZP the symbol is either 1 or -1
取决于x是否是二次剩余的。现在欧拉定理有个坏消息
depending on the quadratic residuosity
of x. Now, the sad thing about Euler's
就是它不是构造性的定理。即使它很可爱
Theorem is that it's not constructive.
Even though it's a very, very cute theorem,
告诉了我们哪些元素是二次剩余的，哪些不是
it tells us exactly which elements are quadratic residues and which
但这个定理没有构建答案
aren't, this theorem doesn't do it
constructively, in the sense that if we
如果我们想计算一个二次剩余的平方根
want to compute the square roots of a
quadratic residue, the theorem doesn't
这个定理并没有告诉我们怎么办。事实上
即使你去看这个定理的证明过程
actually tell us how to do that. And in
fact, even if you look at the proof, the
证明也是基于存在性依据的。那么它只证明了平方根存在
proof is by an existential argument. So it
proves that the square roots exists, but
但没有为我们展示如何计算我们想要的平方根
it doesn't show us how to compute the
square root when we want it.
那么下一个问题是，我们如何计算质数模的平方根
So the next question is then how do we compute square roots modulo primes. So it turns out
实际上，这并不难，它还是分两种情况
that's actually not so hard and, again, it
breaks up into two cases. The first case
第一种情况是，当p=3 mod 4时
is when p is equal to 3 modulo 4
in, which case, it's really easy to
非常容易计算平方根，我将告诉大家有一个简单公式
compute the square root and I'll just tell
you there's a simple formula. The square
这种情况下，c的平方根就是c^((p+1)/4)
root of c in this case is simply c to the
power of (p+1)/4.
大家会注意到因为p=3 mod 4
You'll notice that because p is equal to 3
modulo 4, p+1 is necessarily,
必然有p+1=0 mod 4。意味着p+1被4整除
p+1 is equal to 0 modulo 4.
Which means that p+1 is divisible by
因此(p+1)/4是一个整数
4, and therefore (p+1)/4 is an integer. And that's exactly what allows
这就允许我们计算这个幂，我宣称它给了我们
us to compute this exponentiation, and I
claim that, that actually gives us the
c的平方根。非常简单的公式，直接给我们c的平方根
square root of c. Very simple formula,
that directly gives us the square root of c.
我们来验证一下它的正确性
So let's verify that that's actually true.
我计算c的(p+1)/4次方再平方
Well I'll take c to the power of (p+1)/4 and square that.
事实上，如果c的(p+1)/4次方是c的平方根，
当我求平方时，我应该得到c
And if, in fact, if c to the (p+1)/4 is the square root of c, when I square it, I should get c.
那么我们来看会发生什么。首先，根据指数法则，这就等于
So let's see what happens. So first of all, by laws of exponentiation, this is simply equal to c
c的(p+1)/2次方。我可以写成c^((p-1)/2)*c
to the power of (p+1)/2. And that I can write as c to the power of (p-1)/2 times c
我提取了1/2，移到了幂的外面
Okay, again, this is basically, I took, one-half, and moved it
(其实是提取了1)
现在，关于c的(p-1)/2次方，我们知道什么？
out of the exponentiation. Now, what do we
know about c to the power of (p-1)/2 ?
由于c是二次剩余，我们知道c的(p-1)/2次方是1
Since c is a quadratic residue,
we know that c to the power of (p-1)/2 is 1.
因此，在Z_p中，这等于1乘以c，就是c
And therefore, this is really equal to one times c, which is c in
即为所证。好。那么这就证明了c的(p+1)/4次方
ZP as we wanted to show. Okay. So this
basically proves that c to the power of (p+1)/4
是c的平方根，至少当p=3 mod 4时
is the square root of c, at least in the case when p is equal to 3 modulo 4.
现在大家应该问我，当p=1 mod 4时，答案是什么？
Now you should ask me, well, what about the case when p is equal to 1 mod 4 ?
在这种情况下，这个公式就不成立了。因为指数(p+1)/4
In that case, this formula doesn't even make sense. Because (p+1)/4
这里将是一个有理分式
this exponent here, (p+1)/4 is gonna be a rational fraction, and I don't
我不知道然后计算c的有理分式次方
know how to raise, c to the power of a
rational fraction. Nevertheless, it turns
不过，实际上即使当p=1 mod 4时，我们也可以计算平方根
out that even in the case where p is equal
to 1 mod 4, we can efficiently find
尽管要困难一些。特别地，我们没有
square roots, although it's a little bit
harder. And in particular, we don't have a
确定性的算法来计算。我们必须使用一个随机算法来找
deterministic algorithm to do it. We have
to use a randomized algorithm to do it.
(其实不只一个，比如Tonelli, Cipolla等人的算法)
这个随机算法会非常有效地找到x模p的平方根
But this randomized algorithm will
actually find the square root of x mod p,
我想我应该提到，如果有人能证明
very efficiently. I guess I should mention
that if someone could prove that the
扩展的黎曼猜想，一个更深层的解析数论里的猜想
extended Riemann hypothesis--this is some deep
hypothesis of analytic number theory. If
如果有人能证明这个猜想成立，那么就会给出
someone could prove that, that hypothesis
is true, in fact, it would give a
一个确定的算法来计算平方根，即使p=1 mod 4
deterministic algorithm for computing square roots even when p is equal to 1 modulo 4.
(实际上必须是log p的多项式级的算法。因为即使穷举也是O(p))
我说这个的原因是
So the reason I like to mention that is because you notice that as
(这段话的根据是1992年Victor Shoup的论文Searching for primitive roots in finite fields)
一旦你要研究某个对象的计算
soon as you put the computational lens on
something--for example, I ask you to
例如，计算x模p的平方根。得到一个这样的算法
compute the square roots of a number x
modulo p. Coming up with an algorithm
需要极深的数学结果
already requires extremely, extremely deep
results in mathematics some of which are
甚至是当前未证实的结果。就目前来看
not even known to be true today. So as
things stand today, we simply don't have a
我们还没有一个确定性算法来计算模p平方根，当p=1 mod 4
deterministic algorithm to compute square
roots where p is 1 mod 4. But as I
如我所说，我们有很好的随机算法，这个问题被认为是容易的
said, we have good randomized algorithms,
and this problem is considered easy.
本质上就是算几次幂。因此我们会看到
Essentially, it boils down to a few exponentiations. And as a result, as we'll
计算平方根的运行时间是p的位数的立方
see, the running time of computing square
roots essentially is cubic in the number
很好。现在我们知道如何计算模p的平方根了
of bits of p. So excellence. And now we
know how to compute square roots mod p,
现在我们可以讨论解模p的二次方程了
and so now we can talk about solving
quadratic equations modulo p. So suppose
假设我给你一个二次方程，我让你找到Z_p中
I give you a quadratic equation and I
asked you to find a solution of this
这个二次方程的解。那么现在我宣称，
你已经知道怎么做了
quadratic equation in ZP. Well so now I
claim that you know how to solve it. The
你计算他的方法是使用高中的解二次方程的公式
way you would solve it is basically you
would use the high school formula for
那么方程的解是
solving quadratic equations, you know. So
the solution is minus b plus minus the
(-b±sqrt(b^2-4ac))/(2a)。我说大家知道如何计算的
square root of b squared minus 4ac over
2a. And I claim that you know how to
用这个公式。那么大家知道怎么计算2a的逆
compute all the elements in this formula. So you know how to compute the inverse of 2a.
这样可以除以2a，这是使用的扩展的欧几里德算法
So you can divide by 2a. That's done using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
大家知道如何计算sqrt(b^2-4ac)
And you know how to compute a square root of b squared minus 4ac, using one of
使用上一张幻灯片里的平方根算法
the square root algorithms from the
previous slide. And of course the formula
当然这个公式可解，仅当Z_p中有平方根。很好
will only be solvable if the square root
actually exists in ZP. So that's cool. So
现在大家知道如何解Z_p中的二次方程了
now, you guys know how to solve quadratic
equations in ZP. So now, the next obvious
下一个问题显然是关于计算这些根的，合数模
question is what about computing these
roots, modulo composites rather than
而不是质数模的。那么我们可以问与之前同样的问题
modulo primes. So we can ask exactly the
same questions that we asked before. So
什么时候模N的e次方根存在？如果我们知道它存在
when does the e'th root modulo N exist?
And if we know that it exists, can we
我们能否有效地计算它？这个问题要困难得多了
actually compute it efficiently? And here,
the problem is much, much, much harder.
事实上，我们只知道，计算合数模的e次方根
And in fact it turns out that, for all we
know, computing e'th roots modular
与分解合数一样困难。现在，对于一个普通的数e
composites is in fact as hard as factoring
that composite. Now, for a general e, this
不知道是否是最优的，但我们有的最好的算法
is actually not known to be true, but the
best algorithm that we have for computing
来计算模N的e次方根，需要我们分解这个模
e'th roots modulo N requires us to factor
the modulus. And once we factor the
一旦我们分解了这个模，那么实际上每个质数因数的
modulus, then it's actually easier to
compute e'th roots modulo each of the
e次方根是容易计算的。我们可以组合所有的这些e次方根
prime factors. And we can combine all the
e'th roots together to get the e'th roots
来得到合数模N的e次方根。所以这是个有趣情况
modulo the composite N. So it's a very
interesting case, where computing e'th
计算质数模的e次方根非常容易。事实上，
这对于很多e都非常容易
root modulo prime was very easy. In
fact, for many e's, it was very easy. But
但计算合数模的e次方根困难得多
computing e'th root modulo composite is much, much, much harder and, in fact,
事实上它需要因子分解N。关于e次方根，
这些就是我想告诉大家的
requires the factorization of N. So that's
all I wanted to tell you about e'th roots.
下节我们看模算法
In the next segment, we're gonna turn to
modular algorithms and we're gonna talk
我们将讨论质数模与合数模的加法、乘法和指数算法
about addition and multiplication and exponentiation algorithms, modulo primes and composites.